Inventory of the Inès Keller-Frick papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Inès Keller-Frick papers
1905-1999
90024
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Memoirs, reports, clippings, journal articles, photographs, and printed matter relating to United Nations and Swiss relief work in Poland after World War II; the World War II Serbian resistance leader Draža Mihailovic and his trial and execution in Yugoslavia in 1946; and Swiss foreign relations. Includes memoirs of the Swiss diplomat Albert-Louis Natural.
Keller-Frick, Inès.
Natural, Albert-Louis.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Swiss relief worker; secretary, Schweizer Spende.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, reports, clippings, journal articles, photographs, and printed matter relating to United Nations and Swiss relief work in Poland after World War II; the World War II Serbian resistance leader Draža Mihailovic and his trial and execution in Yugoslavia in 1946; and Swiss foreign relations. Includes memoirs of the Swiss diplomat Albert-Louis Natural.
World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Mihailović, Draža, 1893-1946.; Schweizer Spende (Agency); UNICEF.; International relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Switzerland--Foreign relations.
- Table of contents, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a table of contents created by Keller-Frick naming and outlining the intended arrangement for the documents.
- Introduction by Inès Keller, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  About Draža Mihailović; includes two article clippings.
- Biographical record of General Draža Mihailović (Draza Mihailovich), undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Document 1
  - "Patriot or Traitor: The Case of General Mihailovich," edited by Milorad M. Drachkovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Annexes
    - 1.1 Biographical record of Dr. Milorad Drachkovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1.2 Pilot David O'Connell, newspaper clipping, 1946 July 13 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1.3 T/Sgt. Gus T. Brown, Lt. John P. Devlin, ditto, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1.4 Captain Walter Mansfield and Captain George Musulin, ditto (also see Annex 1.18, "The Mansfield Report"), undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1.5 Staff Sergeant McKool, ditto, 1946 May 17 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1.6 Air Force Lieutenant, Richard L. Feldman, ditto, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1.7 Second Lieutenant, Michael Rajacich, Captain Nick Lalich, Navy Radio Tech, 1c Arthur Jiliian, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1.8 Colonel McDowell's testimony, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      Includes three newpaper clippings related to the testimony.
    - 1.9 Colonel Robert McDowell, article clipping, undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - 1.10 Captain Mansfield's testimony, ditto, 1946 May 14 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - 1.11 Colonel McDowell with General Mihailovich, ditto, 1946 July 15 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - 1.12 "King Peter Asks Truman to Help Save Mihailovich," article clipping, 1946 July 17 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - 1.13 "New York Jury Clears Mihailovich," article clipping, 1946 May 31 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - 1.14 Mihailovich's final plea, ditto, 1946 July 12 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - 1.15 "Death at Belgrade," ditto, 1946 July 20 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - 1.16 "Draja Rejected, Freedom Chance," ditto, 1946 July 19 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - 1.17 "How Reds Seized Stricken Mihailovich by Cowardly Ruse," ditto, 1946 July (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - 1.18 "The Mansfield Report," preface by Boris Todorovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 22)
- Document 2
  - Dr. Ivan Akaumovi, "Mihailovic prema nemackim dokumentima," "Mihailovich in German Documents: Abstract,", undated (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Annexes
    - 2.1 Photocopies of sources, references, books, newspapers and magazines, undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - 2.2 Inès Keller, introduction to the quotations from each of the following works, undated (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - 2.2.1 Kim Philby, Russian mole in British intelligence service, "My Silent War,", undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - 2.2.2 Percy E. Schramm, "Kriegstagebuch des Oberkommandos der Wehrmacht 1939-1945," excerpts, undated (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - 2.2.3 "Wehrmachtsberichte 1933-1945," summary from book, undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - 2.3 Dr. Lazo M. Kostich, "The Holocaust in the Independent State of Croatia,", undated (Box-folder 1: 29)
- Document 3
  - A comment on Mihailovich's restraint to fight the Germans by Mr. Jovan Trboyevic, ex-Lieutenant of the Royal Yugoslav Navy, parachuted into Yugoslavia in 1942, undated (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Annexes
    The table of contents includes Annex 3.1.2, "Geneva Convention of August 12, 1949 on protection of military personnel"; however, the file is missing from the collection.
    - 3.1 Biographical record of Jovan Trboyevic, undated (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - 3.1.1 Geneva Convention of August 12, 1949, on prisoners of war, undated (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - 3.1.3 Protocols additional to Geneva Convention of 12 August 1949, on protection of civilian populations, undated (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - 3.1.4 Geneva Convention of July 27, 1929, relative to the treatment of prisoners of war, undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - 3.1.5 Convention de Genève du 6 juillet 1906 pour l'amèlioration du sort des blessés et malades dans les armées en campagne, undated (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - 3.1.6 Convention de Genève du 22 aout 1864 pour l'amélioration du sort des militaires blessés dans les armées en campagne, undated (Box-folder 1: 35)
- Document 4
  - Rewards promised by the German occupation forces for the capture of either Mihailovich or Tito: 100,000 Reichsmark each, undated (Box-folder 1: 36)
- Document 5
  - Letter from Hitler to Mussolini on February 16, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 37)
- Document 6
  - Order of merit awarded to Mihailovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 38)
- Document 7
  - Nora Beloff, "Tito's Flawed Legacy," Hoover Institution, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Annex
    - 7.1 Biographical record of Nora Beloff, undated (Box-folder 1: 40)
- Document 8
  - Evguenie Yourichitch, "Le procès Tito-Mihailovic" (photocopy under separate cover), 1950 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Annex
    - 8.1 Biographical record of Eugence Yourichitch, undated (Box-folder 1: 42)
- Document 9
  - Branko Lazitch, "La tragédie du General Mihailovic," Hoover Institution, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - Annex
    - 9.1 Biographical record of Branko Lazitch, undated (Box-folder 1: 44)
- Document 10
  - Radomir Petrovic-Kent (Box-folder 1: 45)
    - 1) As former Aide de Camp to H.M. King Peter II of Yugoslavia: "From My 1954 Diary," an account of His Majesty's sorrow for giving in to Churchill, undated
    - 2) As former commander of a brigade under Mihailovich's order during the war: "Military and other memories" [See: Copies, page 150], undated
  - Annexes
    - 10.1 Biographical record of Radomir Petrovic-Kent (Kent was his war alias), undated (Box-folder 1: 46)
    - 10.2 Photocopies of souvenirs, undated (Box-folder 1: 47)
      Includes a picture of Commander Kent during the war, a dollar note signed by the American airmen he saved after an emergency landing, and legitimation of his command of a brigade.
- Document 11
  - "Last Words," by Boris Todorovich, introductory notice by Inès Keller, undated (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - Annexes
    - 11.1 Authorization of reproduction of excerpts from "Last Words" from Ljubica Todorovich, 1989 December 12 (Box-folder 1: 49)
    - 11.2 Excerpts from "Last Words,", undated (Box-folder 1: 50)
    - 11.3 Biographical record of Boris Todorovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 51)
- Document 12
  - Jasper Rootham: "Miss Fire: The Chronicle of a British Mission to Mihailovich, 1943-1944," Hoover Library, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - Annexes
    - 12.1 Biographical record of Jasper Rootham [See: Copies, page 179], undated
- Document 13
  - Agnes Chabrier: "Les pierres crient..." (photocopy of book under separate cover), undated (Box-folder 1: 53)
- Document 14
  - United States press clippings relative to the trial, sentence, and execution of General Drava Mihailovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 54)
- Document 15
  - Swiss press clippings on the case and trial of General Mihailovich, undated (Box-folder 1: 55)
- Document 16
  - "US Congressional Report: Proceedings and Debates: Commemorating 95th Anniversary of Mihailovich's Birth,", 1988 March 29 (Box-folder 1: 56)
- Document 17/18
  - Poems by Milan Rakic
    - 17a. "The Abandoned Church,", undated (Box-folder 1: 57)
    - 17b. "Napustena Crkva,", undated (Box-folder 1: 58)
    - 18a. "Simonida,", undated (Box-folder 1: 59)
    - 18b. "Simonida,", undated (Box-folder 1: 60)
- Copies, undated (Box-folder 1: 61)
  Contains a copy of every document listed in the table of contents, including Document 10 (part 2) and Annex 12.1, which were both missing from their original folders.
- Revue militaire suisse RMS, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 62)
- Récits, études et réflexions du temps que j'étais diplomate 1961-1963, volume I, Albert-Louis Natural, 1998 June (Box-folder 1: 63)
- Récits, études et réflexions du temps que j'étais diplomate 1964-1966, volume II, Albert-Louis Natural, 1998 June (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Récits, études et réflexions du temps que j'étais diplomate 1972-1975, volume III, Albert-Louis Natural, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
  Includes a compact disc copy of the publication.
- Mon séjour en Pologne 1948, Inès Keller-Frick, 1999 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  Includes a typed essay describing his evening with General Bor-Komorowski, who was involved in the Warsaw Insurrection in 1948.
- Die Schweizer Spende, 1944-1948: Polen: [allgemeiner Bericht über Polen], Gertrud Lutz (Box-folder 2: 4)
- "United Nations International Children's Emergency Fund, History of the Mission to Poland," report from UNICEF, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Kosovo, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  Includes a copy of the publication Kosovo 1389-1989, a list of institutions with the same copy, a table of contents, and a typed history abstract.
- Czeslawa Dopieralska, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  Includes a typed personal account of her experiences in World War II, photographs, and excerpts from her book.
- Nürnberg [Nuremberg], 1905-1908 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  Includes a biography of Friedrich Trost and reproductions of his paintings, as well as photos and an informational booklet regarding Heiliggeistkirche, a church in Nuremberg. Photos depict the church before and after the devastation following World War II.
- Photographs, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 2: 9-10)
  Photographs depict the destruction in Warsaw during and after World War II. The majority of the photos have titles written on the back in English describing the location and scene.